<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC1918 SYSTEM
  "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM
  "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM
  "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4864 SYSTEM
  "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4864.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most
     I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info"
     docName="draft-kline-default-perimeter-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
       ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902,
                   noDerivativesTrust200902, or pre5378Trust200902
       you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
       they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only
         necessary if the full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Default Perimeter Identification">
Default Perimeter Identification
    </title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Erik Kline" initials="E." surname="Kline">
      <organization>Google Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <street>Roppongi 6-10-1, 26th Floor</street>
          <city>Minato</city>
          <region>Tokyo</region>
          <code>106-6126</code>
          <country>JP</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+81 03 6384 9000</phone>

        <email>ek@google.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2012" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones,
         xml2rfc will fill in the current day for you. If only the current
         year is specified, xml2rfc will fill in the current day and month
         for you. If the year is not the current one, it is necessary to
         specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified
         for the purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is
         normally sufficient to specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc, IETF is fine for
         individual submissions.  If this element is not present, the default
         is "Network Working Group", which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod
         to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>border</keyword>
    <keyword>homenet</keyword>
    <keyword>perimeter</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
Automatic, simple identification of when traffic is crossing a perimeter
is highly desirable for a variety of home network uses.  This document
proposes a set of default tests to be applied to traffic scheduled for
forwarding, which can be used collectively to identify this perimeter.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
Automatic, simple identification of when traffic is crossing a perimeter
is highly desirable for a variety of home network uses.  This document
proposes a set of default tests to be applied to traffic scheduled for
forwarding, which can be used collectively to identify this perimeter.
      </t>
      <t>
Of note are several limitations introduced by the use of "native"-style
Internet access methods.  By design these architectures make it difficult at
best to distinguish any difference between a LAN port in an enterprise and a
home Internet connection.
      </t>
      <t>
Nevertheless, where practical, an automated mechanism of perimeter discovery
permits home devices to define default definitions of the "interior", i.e.
the home, and the "exterior", usually the greater Internet. Once indentified,
a device could apply default security policies to traffic transiting the
perimeter.
      </t>
      <t>
Specifying a policy that should be applied to traffic crossing this
perimeter is out of scope of this document.  Implementors should remain
mindful of recommended practices, e.g. <xref target="RFC4864">RFC 4864</xref>,
et cetera.
     </t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>
In order to address perimeter identification at a manageable scale the scope
has been limited to discussing concepts of "interior", "exterior", and
"perimeter".  Working definitions in use by this document are as follows.
      </t>

      <t>
        <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Interior">
          <vspace blankLines="0" />
The interior is broadly defined to include the collection of interfaces
(physical or virtual), nodes, and forwarding next-hops collectively under the
control of a single logical administrative domain.
          </t>

          <t hangText="Exterior">
          <vspace blankLines="0" />
The exterior is broadly defined to include all interfaces (physical or virtual),
nodes, and forwarding next-hops collectively NOT under the control of any
single logical administrative domain and specifically NOT under the control
of the administrative domain which defines the interior.
          </t>

          <t hangText="Perimeter">
          <vspace blankLines="0" />
The perimeter is taken to be the collection of all ephemeral demarcations
within the collection of interior nodes which forward traffic such that any IP
packet transiting that demarcation can be said to be crossing either from the
interior toward the exterior or from the exterior toward the interior.  This
is independent of whether or not such traffic is permitted by policy to
complete its transiting from one zone to the other.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
Expressly not discussed herein are concepts of multiple interior networks,
nor any relationships between them as separate from their relationship to
their common exterior or any common perimeter.  The architectures under
discussion have a single interior, single exterior, and a single perimeter.
      </t>

      <t>
The definition of perimeter is such that, for example, an IP packet arriving
on a NAT device's interior interface that is "hairpinned" and retransmitted
out the interior interface is not considered to have touched nor crossed
the perimeter.
      </t>

      <t>
The definition of perimeter as written technically permits traffic being
forwarded over an interface to be classified as transiting a perimeter or
not based on the classification of the next-hop.  The implications of this
are discussed in TBD.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Fundamental recommendations">
      <section title="Network node default security practices">
        <t>
By default all network nodes SHOULD follow best current security practices.
Any node may at times find itself in a hostile environment.  This is obviously
true of mobile nodes when, for instance, connecting to a variety of public
"Wi-Fi" networks.  In such environments mobile nodes cannot be sure that
network device is acting in its own best security interests with respect to
others on the local network.
        </t>
        <t>
It is equally true of more traditionally "fixed" nodes: any compromised
neighbor nodes ("fixed" or mobile) may be used as a conduit for further
compromise.  Indeed, one study of a captured "botnet"
(<xref target="TORPIG" />, section 5.2.4) found that roughly 78.9% of infected
hosts had <xref target="RFC1918">RFC 1918</xref> addresses, commmonly used in
IPv4 NAT deployments.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Logging">
        <t>
Nodes compliant with this and other homenet documents SHOULD administratively
log the perimeter classification of interfaces (both physical and virtual),
the reason(s) for such classification, and times at which such classifications
are made or changed.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Useful perimeter signals">
      <t>
This is a non-trivial task as it is tantamount to automated discovery of
administrative boundaries.
      </t>

      <t>
Many architectures fundamentally make it difficult or impossible to detect
administrative boundaries and rely on various mechanisms of user or
administrator invention to create or modify such boundaries.  Other hints
about administrative boundaries are insecure, unreliable, or impractical.
[router peering and reverse IP DNS delegation examples]
      </t>

      <t>
Nevertheless there are some guidelines that may be useful, though it is
stressed that nothing is likely to be more secure than boundary detection
by way of authenticated communication protocols (e.g. an authenticated
interior routing protocol).
      </t>

      <t>
This document discusses interfaces, traffic traversing them, whether doing
so should be considered as crossing a perimeter, and which interfaces are
"interior" versus "exterior".  There may be multiple interior interfaces as
well as multiple exterior interfaces.  Notions of perimeter between pairs of
exterior interfaces are out of scope, as are notions of perimeter between
multiple interior interfaces (e.g., a home router with wired and "guest"
wireless networks).
      </t>

      <section title="Links requiring subscriber information">
        <t>
Perhaps the most obvious administrative boundary is a link that requires
subscriber credentials in order for that link to successfully forward and
receive general traffic.  Examples include authenticated PPPoE sessions,
3G/LTE PDP contexts (requiring a SIM card associated with a customer account),
and authenticated VPN links.  By default, all traffic traversing such a link
SHOULD be considered to be traversing a boundary.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Links requiring existing IP-layer connectivity">
        <t>
E.g. Teredo, 6to4, 6rd, 4rd, PPTP/L2TP tunnels, ...
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Routing adjacency">
        <t>
authenticated, secure
Undoubtedly the most reliable method for perimeter detection may be all
interfaces that form an authenticated adjacency to...

Discuss: [two routers each sharing a hub with two upstreams on it]
        </t>

        <t>
Routing protocol could further define security zones so that the rules among
interiors and among exteriors could be defined...
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="on-link neighbor communications">
        <t>
Most home networking technology supports two nodes on the same logical link
communicating directly.  By default, traffic traversing from such a link to
one on which no on-link neighbor discovery and/or communication is permitted,
either by design (e.g. a point-to-point link) or administrative choice
(e.g. an 802.11 SSID on which the infrastructural access point forbids direct
neighbor communications) SHOULD be considered as crossing an administrative
boundary and therefore SHOULD be considered as crossing a security perimeter.
        </t>

        <t>
Discuss: same for tunneled protocols where "point-to-point" isn't necessarily
a requirement, e.g. 6to4.
        </t>

        <t>
Note that it would be insecure to consider a link on which a default router
had disabled on-link determination via flags in the IPv6 RA as changing from
security perimeter to interior as such a router may not actually be part of
the interior's administrative domain.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Product-defined interface purposes">
        <t>
Many products come with interfaces labeled with their intended use.  Examples
include home routers with RJ-45 ports labeled "WAN" and "LAN", or perhaps
with symbols indicating "The Internet" and "inside the home".  Other examples
include wireless routers with defined WLAN and "Guest" ESSIDs.  In such cases
where concepts of "interior" and "exterior" are clearly implied a homenet
router SHOULD by default consider traffic forwarded between interfaces of
differing regions as traversing a boundary.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="DHCPv6 PD, if and only if...">
        <t>
DHCPv6 PD is at this time the most common method for supplying SoHo networks
with a routable prefix block.
        </t>

        <t>
If (and only if) a means of distributing prefixes among interior routers is
devised that does NOT use DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation, then a link on which
DHCPv6 PD succeeded SHOULD be considered an administrative boundary and
traffic traversing this interface SHOULD be considered to be traversing a
security perimeter.
        </t>

        <t>
If PD is to be used within the interior where a single security policy is
desired to be in effect, then this signal is not useful.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Additional considerations">
      <section title="Physical vs virtual interfaces">
        <t>
In certain configurations it may be desirable that the perimeter defined on
a virtual interface also be extended to include the physical interface(s) over
which such traffic is forwarded/received.  For example, consider a router
configured with a PPPoE virtual interface on a physical 802.3 interface.  In
such a configuration, the security policy applied to traffic transitting the
PPPoE interface should most likely also be applied to non-PPPoE traffic
transitting the physical interface.  If not, the "interior" region would
otherwise be logically extended to include the upstream access link.  As there
is no guaranteed of administrative boundary XXX, a default configuration
SHOULD consider the physical interface a perimeter.
        </t>

        <t>
By way of contrast, consider an entirely interior router which also has a
VPN interface, through which traffic may be passed to, say, a resident's
company network.  While a VPN virtual interface SHOULD be considered a
logical demarcation point, the physical interface through which
VPN-encapsulated traffic is transmitted need not necessarily be classified
as such.  Instead, what may be desired is that traffic to/from interfaces that
are interior to this VPN-enabled router may pass through either the VPN
interface or any "upstream" interfaces, but traffic originating from "upstream"
interfaces may be default DENIED transit through the VPN interface.  While
this situation may be far from the norm for networks, it nevertheless affords
the maintenance of a simple mental model of a hierarchical network.
        </t>

        <t>
To address these uses, by default the physical interface(s) through which
a virtual interface's traffic is forward should also be considered a
perimeter, unless other means determine that it is in fact an interior
interface.  Note that in all cases such a virtual interface is considered
a perimeter.
        </t>

        <t>
Discuss: applying the policy to the entire interface for some "infrastructural"
connections (e.g. PPPoE).  Virtual link versus physical link, virtual interface
versus physical interface.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Mixed zone next-hops on the same interface">
        <t>
By default, if one then all.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Perimeter and address families">
        <t>
Same in IPvv4 and IPv6.  Anything else will violate principle of least
surprise, and may lead to a deployment in an insecure configuration.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Ignore these old scribblings">
      <t>
Assumptions include:
      </t>
      <t>
A mechanism exists to manually override these defaults.
RA-guard is sensibly, universally in effect.
Something other than DHCPv6-PD will be used within the home (eventually)
to distribute prefixes.
By default, unless manually configured otherwise, traffic received or to be
sent:
via interfaces which are point-to-point (e.g., PPP(oE) interfaces,
L2TP/VPNs/tunnels in general, et cetera), or
via next-hops which issued an RA in which on-link computation was disabled
(TODO: exception text for link types where !on-link is normal, e.g.
LLN if the forwarding device in question is, say, a 6LBR), or
via interfaces from which a prefix has been delegated via DHCPv6-PD, or
via interfaces which have NO RFC3484(bis) global scope addresses of the same
family as the passing traffic, or
via next-hops which are NOT participating in an authenticated routing domain,
when an authenticated routing domain is otherwise in use,
MUST be considered as crossing a perimeter.

TODO: see if we can rewrite this as an ordered set of tests or rules.
[RTDDOM] By default, unless manually configured otherwise, traffic received
from or to be sent via next-hops which are NOT participating in an
authenticated routing domain when an authenticated routing domain is
otherwise in use SHOULD be considered as crossing a perimeter.
[PPPTUN] By default, unless manually configured otherwise, traffic received
or to be sent via interfaces which are point-to-point in nature or
are tunnel/encapsulated interfaces SHOULD be considered as crossing a perimeter.
Examles of interfaces that by default would form a perimeter include
PPP, PPPoE, PPPoA, L2TP tunnel interfaces, and typical VPN interfaces.
This also includes Teredo, 6to4, 6rd, and 4rd interfaces.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="simple_list" title="Simple List">
      <t>
List styles: 'empty', 'symbols', 'letters', 'numbers', 'hanging', 'format'.
      </t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>First bullet</t>

          <t>Second bullet</t>
        </list> You can write text here as well.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Figures">
      <t>Figures should not exceed 69 characters wide to allow for the indent
      of sections.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="xml_happy">
        <preamble>Preamble text - can be omitted or empty.</preamble>

        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
+-----------------------+
| Use XML, be Happy :-) |
|_______________________|
            ]]></artwork>

        <postamble>Cross-references allowed in pre- and postamble. <xref
        target="min_ref" />.</postamble>
      </figure>

      <t>The CDATA means you don't need to escape meta-characters (especially
      &lt;&nbsp;(&amp;lt;) and &amp;&nbsp;(&amp;amp;)) but is not essential.
      Figures may also have a title attribute but it won't be displayed unless
      there is also an anchor. White space, both horizontal and vertical, is
      significant in figures even if you don't use CDATA.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- This PI places the pagebreak correctly (before the section title)
         in the text output. -->

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

    <section title="Subsections and Tables">
      <section title="A Subsection">
        <t>By default 3 levels of nesting show in table of contents but that
        can be adjusted with the value of the "tocdepth" processing
        instruction.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Tables">
        <t>.. are very similar to figures:</t>

        <texttable anchor="table_example" title="A Very Simple Table">
          <preamble>Tables use ttcol to define column headers and widths.
          Every cell then has a "c" element for its content.</preamble>

          <ttcol align="center">ttcol #1</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">ttcol #2</ttcol>

          <c>c #1</c>

          <c>c #2</c>

          <c>c #3</c>

          <c>c #4</c>

          <c>c #5</c>

          <c>c #6</c>

          <postamble>which is a very simple example.</postamble>
        </texttable>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="nested_lists" title="More about Lists">
      <t>Lists with 'hanging labels': the list item is indented the amount of
      the hangIndent: <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="short">With a label shorter than the hangIndent.</t>

          <t hangText="fantastically long label">With a label longer than the
          hangIndent.</t>

          <t hangText="vspace_trick"><vspace blankLines="0" />Forces the new
          item to start on a new line.</t>
        </list></t>

      <!-- It would be nice to see the next piece (12 lines) all on one page.
        -->

      <?rfc needLines="12" ?>

      <t>Simulating more than one paragraph in a list item using
      &lt;vspace&gt;: <list style="letters">
          <t>First, a short item.</t>

          <t>Second, a longer list item.<vspace blankLines="1" /> And
          something that looks like a separate pararaph..</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Simple indented paragraph using the "empty" style: <list
          hangIndent="10" style="empty">
          <t>The quick, brown fox jumped over the lazy dog and lived to fool
          many another hunter in the great wood in the west.</t>
        </list></t>

      <section title="Numbering Lists across Lists and Sections">
        <t>Numbering items continuously although they are in separate
        &lt;list&gt; elements, maybe in separate sections using the "format"
        style and a "counter" variable.</t>

        <t>First list: <list counter="reqs" hangIndent="4" style="format R%d">
            <t>#1</t>

            <t>#2</t>

            <t>#3</t>
          </list> Specify the indent explicitly so that all the items line up
        nicely.</t>

        <t>Second list: <list counter="reqs" hangIndent="4" style="format R%d">
            <t>#4</t>

            <t>#5</t>

            <t>#6</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Where the List Numbering Continues">
        <t>List continues here.</t>

        <t>Third list: <list counter="reqs" hangIndent="4" style="format R%d">
            <t>#7</t>

            <t>#8</t>

            <t>#9</t>

            <t>#10</t>
          </list> The end of the list.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

<!--
    <section anchor="codeExample"
             title="Example of Code or MIB Module To Be Extracted">
      <figure>
        <preamble>The &lt;artwork&gt; element has a number of extra attributes
        that can be used to substitute a more aesthetically pleasing rendition
        into HTML output while continuing to use the ASCII art version in the
        text and nroff outputs (see the xml2rfc README for details). It also
        has a "type" attribute. This is currently ignored except in the case
        'type="abnf"'. In this case the "artwork" is expected to contain a
        piece of valid Augmented Backus-Naur Format (ABNF) grammar. This will
        be syntax checked by xml2rfc and any errors will cause a fatal error
        if the "strict" processing instruction is set to "yes". The ABNF will
        also be colorized in HTML output to highlight the syntactic
        components. Checking of additional "types" may be provided in future
        versions of xml2rfc.</preamble>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

/**** an example C program */

#include <stdio.h>

void
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    int i;

    printf("program arguments are:\n");
    for (i = 0; i < argc; i++) {
        printf("%d: \"%s\"\n", i, argv[i]);
    }

    exit(0);
} /* main */

/* end of file */

            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>
-->

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
The author gratefully acknowledges the constructive input and criticism of
Lorenzo Colitti, Mark Townsley, and Ole Troan.
      </t>
      <t>
Thanks also must go to pleasant, peaceful and productive trips on the
Japan Rail (JR) Shinkansen ("bullet train").
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
This memo includes no request to IANA.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>All drafts are required to have a security considerations section.
      See <xref target="RFC3552">RFC 3552</xref> for a guide.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      &RFC2119;

      <reference anchor="min_ref">
        <!-- the following is the minimum to make xml2rfc happy -->

        <front>
          <title>Minimal Reference</title>

          <author initials="authInitials" surname="authSurName">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2006" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->

      &RFC1918;

      &RFC3552;

      &RFC4864;

      <reference anchor="TORPIG"
           target="http://www.cs.ucsb.edu/~seclab/projects/torpig/torpig.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>
Your Botnet is My Botnet: Analysis of a Botnet Takeover
          </title>

          <author initials="B" surname="Stone-Gross">
            <organization>University of California, Santa Barbara
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="app-additional" title="Additional Stuff">
      <t>This becomes an Appendix.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
